Finding Aid to the Jacob M. Ulmer Papers, 1949-1969
History of Medicine Division, National Library of Medicine.
Jacob M. Ulmer Papers Relating to the promotion and funding of research to prevent blindness 1949-1969
Ulmer, Jacob M. 1886-1972
34 MS boxes and 62 v.
MS C 225
History of Medicine Division. National Library of Medicine
Jacob Ulmer was secretary of the National Foundation for Eye Research and served on the National Advisory Neurological Diseases and Blindness Council. Contains correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and printed material on ophthalmology, medical research, rehabilitation of the blind, and persons and organizations active in those fields in the United States and abroad.
Provenance
Gift of J. M. Ulmer, 1969.
Restrictions
Collection is not restricted. Contact the Reference Staff for information regarding access.
Biographical Note
Jacob M. Ulmer was born in Shreve, OH, 19 November 1886 and died in 1972. He received his LLB from Western Reserve University's Franklin Thomas Backus School of Law in 1908. A lawyer by training and profession, cataracts developed in Ulmer's eyes and he began to go blind in 1946. After several operations to remove the cataracts, Ulmer began investigating the state of eye disease research and discovered that over 75% of all the blinding diseases were unknown to science. He decided that something had to be done about the state of opthomological research and since then devoted the rest of his life to the field.
In 1949, Ulmer, along with Al Hirshberg (another layman) and Dr. V. Everett Kinsey (Howe Laboratory of Opthamology, Harvard Medical School) joined forces and created the National Foundation for Eye Research in Washington, D.C. The group immediately began looking for the finances to support their eye research proposals. Several groups came to their aid, most notably the Lasker Foundation. With the personal support of Albert and Mary Lasker and the Lasker Foundation, Ulmer lobbied Congress to create an institute on blindness. In 1950 Public Law 692 was passed, establishing the National Institute for Neurological Diseases and Blindness under the Public Health Service. In 1968, the National Eye Institute became a separate institute.
Ulmer also had a profound affect on the operational structure of NIH itself. After establishing NINDB, Ulmer proposed a revolutionary method of financing medical research. His idea was for NINDB to distribute grant money directly to individual medical schools and research institutes to foster eye research projects. Medical schools were at first sceptical, fearing NIH was trying to take control their activities after making them dependent on the grant money. After much negotiating between the schools and and extensive study performed by NIH's Inter-Council Committee on Institutional Grants, the idea of "block grants" was instituted, whereby grants applicants spelled out who was receiving the funds, who the researchers were, scope of the project, etc., so that when the grant was made the researchers were free of any interference by NIH. This method of encouraging research via institutional grants changed forever how NIH operated and helped foster its own prominence in the scientific world.
Ulmer spent the remainder of his life devoted to educating himself and the world about the treatment of blindness and eye disease. It was mainly through his efforts that physicians changed their focus from simply rehabilitating the blind to seeking out the causes of blindness and developing treatments and cures.
Collection Summary
Papers are arranged into 7 series: I. General, II. Correspondence and papers, III. Miscellaneous papers, IV. Clippings and miscellaneous data, V. International papers and correspondence, VI. Congressional papers, VII. Bound volumes.
Papers contain correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and printed material on ophthalmology, medical research, rehabilitation of the blind, and persons and organizations active in those fields in the United States and abroad.
Correspondents include Silas Adelsheim, Pearce Bailey, Harold T. Clark, Charles Austin Doan, Stewart Duke-Elder, Edwin B. Dunphy, Novice G. Fawcett, Jonas S. Friedenwald, William Henry Havener, Lister Hill, Victor Everett Kinsey, Richard L. Masland, Leonard A. Scheele, Frederick Logan Stone, Derrick Vail, and C. J. Van Slyke. Organizations represented are the American Foundation for the Blind, the Howe Laboratory of Ophthalmology, the National Committee for Research in Neurological Disorders, the National Institute of Neurological Diseases and Blindness, the Ohio State University Institute for Research in Vision, and the Retina Foundation.
Index Terms
These terms are indexed in the National Library of Medicine's online catalog LocatorPlus. Researchers wishing to find related materials should search the catalog using these terms.
MeSH Subjects
Diseases / Eye; Ophthalmology
Personal Names
Havener, William H. (William Henry), 1924-; Kinsey, Victor Everett, 1909-; Stone, Frederick Logan, 1915-
Corporate Names
Lasker Foundation; National Foundation for Eye Research; National Institute of Neurological Diseases and Blindness (U.S.); Ohio. State University. Columbus. Institute for Research in Vision
Series Descriptions
- General, 1949-1969
  - Biographical Data (Box 01)
  - "other people's opinions" (Box 01)
  - Interview with Wyndham D. Miles, April 1969 (Box 01)
  - Volume of general data relating to collection (Box 01)
  - Volumes 1-3, newspaper clippings and data related to eye research (Box 01)
  - Report-Inter-Council Committee of Institutional Grants, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Study and report, retrolental fibroplasia. "America's first national program in eye research" (Box 1)
  - Volume: Miscellaneous data on prevention of blindness thru research, with index (Box 1)
  - Notes, drafts, memoranda (Box 1)
  - Reports, speeches, and papers (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Papers, 1949-1969
  - Adelsheim, S., 1949-1958 (Box 1)
  - Adelsheim, S., 1959-1967 (Box 2)
  - Adler, A. (Box 2)
  - Adler, F.H. (Box 2)
  - Alexander, E.B., Optometric Extension Program (Box 2)
  - Allen, E.M. (Box 2)
  - Allen, J.H. (Box 2)
  - American Association of Ophthalmology (Box 2)
  - American Contract Bridge League, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - American Association for the Blind, 1949-1969
    - Correspondence
      - General, A - Z (Box 2)
      - Barnett, M.R., 1949-1958 (Box 2)
      - Irwin, R.B. (Box 2)
      - Walker, H.C. (Box 2)
    - Publications (Box 2-3)
  - American Foundation for the Overseas Blind (Box 3)
  - American Foundation Studies (Box 3)
    - -- Medical Research: A Mid-Century Survey - Reviews
  - American Foundations Information Service (Box 3)
  - American Foundations News, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - American Medical Association (Box 3)
  - Animal Experimentation - Reprints and miscellaneous data (Box 3)
  - Arthritis and Rheumatism Foundation (Box 3)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges (Box 3)
  - Bailey, P., 1951-1960 (Box 3)
  - Bayne-Jones, S. (Box 4)
  - Burney, L.E. (Box 4)
  - Carroll, T.J. - "Cerebral Death; Theological Considerations" (Box 4)
  - Clark, H.T. and clippings, 1948-1960 (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Mental Health Association (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Metropolitan General Hospital (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Mount Sinai Hospital (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Plain Dealer (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Press
    - General (Box 4)
    - Seltzer, L.B. (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Society for the Blind (Box 4)
  - Cogan, D.g., 1951-1970 (Box 4)
  - Commonwealth Fund (Box 4)
  - Cummings, M.M. (Box 4)
  - Deignan, S.L., 1949-1959 (Box 4)
  - Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1956-1969, n.d.
    - Annual Report, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Children's Bureau (Box 5)
    - Medical Research Activities (Box 5)
    - Office of Education Publications (Box 5)
    - Report, Resources for medical research (Box 5)
  - Dow Corning Center for Aid to Medical Research, 1959-1969 (Box 5)
  - Duke-Elder, S., 1949-1967 (Box 5)
  - Dunphy, E.B., 1950-1968 (Box 5)
  - Excerpta Medica, 1952-1956
    - Correspondence, 1952-1956 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 5)
  - Eye Bank for Sight Restoration, Inc
    - Correspondence, 1952-1960 (Box 5)
    - Manual (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 6)
  - Eye Banks
    - Correspondence, A - W (Box 6)
    - Fact Sheets (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 6)
  - Eye Banks - Rochester
    - Correspondence, 1952-1959 (Box 6)
    - Publications (Box 6)
  - Federal Register. New Drug Regulations, 1963
  - Federal Register. Reprints re: Food and Drug Administration and drug abuse, 1963-1968 (Box 6)
  - Federal Register. Reprints re: Food and Drug Administration and drug abuse, 1969 (Box 7)
  - Federal Security Agency (Box 7)
    - -- Office of Vocational Rehabilitation and Social Security Administration - Publications
  - Felix, R.H., 1951-1964 (Box 7)
  - Flemming, A.S. (Box 7)
  - Food and Drug Administration. Proceedings of Conference on 1965 Drug Abuse Control Amendments, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Friedenwald, J.S. (Box 7)
  - Fulbright Professors (Box 7)
  - Gans, J. (Box 7)
  - Glaucoma Survey - Cleveland (Box 7)
  - Grant, W. Morton (Box 7)
  - Gregg, Alan, 1950-1960 (Box 7)
  - Health Information Foundation
    - An Inventory of Social and Economic Research in Health, 1952 (Box 7)
    - "Progress in Health Services", 1956-1966 (Box 7)
  - Hinsey, J.C.
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Articles (Box 7)
  - Howe Laboratory of Ophthalmology
    - Correspondence, 1958-1970 (Box 7)
    - Application for research grant (Box 8)
    - Program (Box 8)
    - 1964 Report (Box 8)
  - Illinois Society for Medical Research, 1962-1969
    - Bulletins, 1962-1969 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 8)
  - Imus, H.A. (Box 8)
  - Institute for Advancement of Medical Communication (Box 8)
  - Johnson, L.V. (Box 8)
  - Kellogg Foundation (Box 8)
  - Kennedy, President J.F. and Lee C. White (Box 8)
  - Keppel, F. (Box 8)
  - Kinsey, V.E., 1948-1968
    - Correspondence, 1948-1968 (Box 8)
    - Retrolental Fibrolasia Project (Box 8)
  - Kintner, K. (Box 8)
  - Knights Templar
    - Correspondence
      - Delamater, W.A., 1956-1962 (Box 9)
      - Wieber, L.H. (Box 9)
  - Kloss, A.G. (Box 9)
  - Kresge Eye Institute Publications (Box 9)
  - Lanning, L. McC, 1951-1960 (Box 9)
  - Lape, E.E, 1955-1958 (Box 9)
  - Lasker, M., 1949-1961
    - Correspondence, 1949-1961 (Box 9)
    - Clippings (Box 9)
    - Factsheet on Blindness (Box 9)
  - Lasker Awards
    - General (Box 9)
    - "Out of Darkness" (Box 9)
    - "Wassaic Story" (Box 9)
  - Lasker Foundation
    - Correspondence
      - Fordyce, A. (Box 9)
      - Mantell, H. (Box 9)
      - McDonough, J.E. (Box 9)
      - Zikmund, H.L. (Box 9)
  - Lions Club
    - Indiana (Box 9)
    - Massachusetts, 1951-1956 (Box 9)
    - Ohio
      - Publications (Box 10)
      - Steece, E. (Box 10)
  - Lions Clubs (Box 10)
  - Lions International (Box 10)
  - Masland, R.L., 1959-1967 (Box 10)
  - Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary (Box 10)
  - Mayo, L.W. (Box 10)
  - Muscular Dystrophy Associations of America, Inc. (Box 10)
  - Mutual Security Program (Box 10)
  - National Committee for Research in Eye Diseases and Disabilities (Box 10)
  - National Committee for Research in Neurological Disorders. Chiefly correspondence with A.B. Baker, 1952-1966 (Box 10)
  - National Committee for Research in Neurological Disorders, 1966-1967 (Box 11)
    - -- Program
  - National Committee for Research in Ophthalmology and Blindness, 1957-1967 (Box 11)
  - National Conference on Cardiovascular Disease (Box 11)
  - National Council to Combat Blindness
    - General information (Box 11)
    - Correspondence - Wisenfeld, M., 1946-1967 (Box 11)
  - National Foundation for Eye Research, 1948-1957 (Box 11)
  - National Health Education Committee, Inc. - Publications (Box 12)
  - National Heart Institute - Publications (Box 13)
  - National Institute of Neurological Diseases and Blindness
    - Advisory Council, 1950-1951 (Box 13)
    - Booklet - "Exploring the Brain of Man" (Box 13)
    - Budgets and other information, 1955-1968 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 13)
    - Publications (Box 13)
    - Reports (Box 13)
    - NINDB Review, 1963-1966 (Box 13)
  - National Institutes of Health
    - Clippings (Box 13)
    - Inter-Council Committee on Institutional Grants, 1950-1952
      - Correspondence1950-1952 (Box 13)
      - Report, 1952 (Box 13)
      - Scrapbook compiled by Ulmer (Box 13)
      - Notebooks (Box 14)
    - National Advisory Research Resources Committee (Box 14)
    - News Releases, 1949-1968 (Box 14)
    - Publications and Information (Box 14)
    - Scientific Directories, 1964, 1967 (Box 14)
    - Woolridge Committee Report (Box 14)
  - National Library of Medicine - MEDLARS information (Box 14)
  - National Medical Foundation for Eye Care
    - Correspondence and miscellaneous (Box 14)
    - Jaeckle, C.E. (Box 15)
    - Publications (Box 15)
    - News Bulletin, 1961-1965 (Box 15)
  - National Multiple Sclerosis Society
    - Correspondence
      - Lawry, S. (Box 15)
      - Traeger, C. (Box 15)
    - Publications (Box 15)
  - National Neurological Research Foundation (Box 15)
  - National Science Foundation, n.d., 1955
    - Annual Reports (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 15)
  - National Society for Crippled Children (Box 15)
  - National Society for the Prevention of Blindness
    - Correspondence (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous Publications (Box 15)
  - Naval Research Technical Reports re: Ophthalmology (Box 15)
  - Nestingen, I.A. (Box 16)
  - New York Association for the Blind (Box 16)
  - New York Guild for the Jewish Blind (Box 16)
  - New York Institute for the Education of the Blind - "No More Light" (Box 16)
  - Newell, F.W.
    - Correspondence, 1955-1968 (Box 16)
    - National Committee for Research in Ophthalmology and Blindness (Box 16)
  - Nixon, R.M. (Box 16)
  - Office of Technical Services (Dept. of Commerce)
    - OTS Selective Bibliography (Box 16)
  - Ohio State Correspondence, 1950-1958
    - DiSalle, M.V., 1958-1962 (Box 16)
    - Ferguson, D. McK. (Box 16)
    - Lausche, F.J. (Box 16)
    - McClure, J.F. (Box 16)
    - Porterfield, J.D., 1950-1957 (Box 16)
    - Steece, E.R. (Box 16)
    - Others, A-Z (Box 16)
  - Ohio State Legislature - Name Lists and Ulmer letters (Box 16)
  - Ohio State - Services for Preschool Blind Children (Box 16)
  - Ohio State University
    - Correspondence
      - Collins, A.D. - re: medical ethics and College of Optometry (Box 17)
      - Culler, A.M., 1949-1953 (Box 17)
      - Doan, C.A.1949-1961 (Box 17)
      - Fawcett, N.G.1958-1965 (Box 17)
      - Havener, W.H., 1955-1967
        - Correspondence, 1955-1967 (Box 17)
        - Publications and printed matter (Box 17)
      - Meiling, R.L. (Box 17)
      - Others, A - T (Box 17)
    - Hospitals (Box 18)
    - Institute for Research in Vision (Box 18)
    - Ophthalmology (Box 18)
    - Printed Matter re: Optometry (Box 18)
  - "Ohio Story" Radio Program (Box 18)
  - Ophthalmology Foundation, Inc., 1943-1959
    - Annual Reports and miscellaneous, 1943-1951 (Box 18)
    - Berens, C., 1947-1957 (Box 18)
    - Tolman, C.P., 1958-1959 (Box 18)
  - Optometry - miscellaneous
    - Information Re: Ohio State controversy (Box 18)
  - Papian, W.N. - Computer Technology (Box 18)
  - Perkins Institution (Box 18)
  - Permanent Charity Fund - Year Book for 1961 (Box 18)
  - Perrott, G. St. J. (Box 18)
  - Porterfield, J.D. (Box 18)
  - Potts, A.M. (Box 18)
  - Price, D.E., 1950-1964 (Box 18)
  - Proctor Foundation for Research in Ophthalmology (Box 19)
  - Public Health Service
    - Eighth Annual Report of the Surgeon General, 1964 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous publications (Box 19)
    - Grants and Awards, 1967 (Box 19)
    - Research Grants and Fellowships, 1941-1955 (Box 19)
    - Impact of Public Health Grant Programs on Medical Research and Education. Report of Interstate and Foreign Commerce Committee (Box 19)
  - Putnam, P. (Box 19)
  - Radiation accidents - Information (Box 19)
  - Reader's Digest correspondence, 1950-1962 (Box 19)
  - Research to Prevent Blindness, Inc
    - Correspondence (Box 19)
    - Stein, J. (Box 19)
    - Stein, J. - Clippings (Box 19)
  - Retina Foundation
    - Correspondence, chiefly with C.L. Schepens (Box 20)
    - Description of Eye Research (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material (Box 20)
    - Report for 1964-1965, 1964-1965 (Box 20)
  - Retrolental Fibroplasia Study (Box 20)
  - Robert, L. (Box 20)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1947-1958 (Box 20)
  - Rockefeller, N.A. (Box 20)
  - Scheele, L.A., 1950-1962 (Box 20)
  - Schilling, Capt. C.W., 1950-1955 (Box 20)
  - Sebrell, W.H. (Box 20)
  - Sherman, A.W. (Box 20)
  - Sloan Foundation (Box 20)
    - -- Zurcher, A.J., 1955-1965
  - Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer Research (Box 21)
  - Smelser, G.K. (Box 21)
  - Social Legislation Information Service. Washington Bulletin, 1957-1969 (Box 21)
  - Stone, F.L., 1951-1965
    - Correspondence, 1951-1965 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 22)
  - Stone, W., Jr., 1952-1963
    - Correspondence, 1952-1963 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 22)
  - Swan, K.C. (Box 22)
  - Symposium on Research in Blindness and Severe Visual Impairment (Box 22)
  - Tankersley, Mrs. G.E. (Box 22)
  - Thygeson, P. (Box 22)
  - Trachoma data (Box 22)
  - Tufts-New England Medical Center News (Box 22)
  - Vail, D., 1952-1963 (Box 22)
  - Van Slyke, C.J., 1949-1963 (Box 22)
  - Volk, David (Box 22)
  - Watizman, M.B. (Box 22)
  - Warren, S.L. (Box 23)
  - Western Reserve University - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - Williams, G. (Box 23)
  - Winter, N. (Box 23)
  - Woods, A.C., 1950-1958 (Box 23)
  - World Federation of Neurology - Reports (Box 23)
  - World Health Organization - Newsletter, 1955-1956 (Box 23)
  - Zacharias, L., 1952-1958 (Box 23)
- Miscellaneous papers and correspondence
  - Ab - Fr (Includes A. Celebrezze) (Box 23)
  - G - Z (includes H. Hoover, H. Keller) (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Sized Items
    - National Institutes of Health
      - Research Projects Grants Awarded to Foreign Institutions and International Organizations, 1962 (Box 24)
      - Research at the National Institutes of Health (Box 24)
    - Parke Davis Co. A History of Medicine in Pictures (Box 24)
    - Roche Medical Image, 1962 (Box 24)
    - Western Reserve University Medical Center (Box 24)
- Clippings and Miscellaneous data
  - Blindness - rehabilitation (Box 25)
  - Cancer (Box 25)
  - Cataracts (Box 25)
  - Cerebral Palsy (Box 25)
  - Computers (Box 25)
  - Contact lenses (Box 25)
  - Corneal diseases, transplants (Box 25)
  - Cryosurgery (Box 25)
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (Box 25)
  - Diseases (Box 25)
  - Drug Control (Box 25)
  - Drugs - use and abuse (Box 25)
  - Education, general (Box 25)
  - Educatioin, medical (Box 25)
  - Education, science (Box 26)
  - Eye care (Box 26)
  - Eye diseases (Box 26)
  - Eye research (Box 26)
  - Food and Drug Administration (Box 26)
  - Foreign aid (Box 26)
  - Foundations (Box 26)
  - Glaucoma (Box 26)
  - Heart disease (Box 26)
  - Lasers (Box 26)
  - Legal medicine (Box 26)
  - Medicare (Box 26)
  - Medicine, general (Box 26)
  - Mental health, psychology, behavior (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
  - Multiple sclerosis (Box 26)
  - Ophthalmology (Box 26)
  - Optometry (Box 26)
  - Physiology (Box 26)
  - Research, general (Box 26)
  - Research Facilities (Box 27)
  - Research Funds, Support of Medical Research: A Symposium (Published by the Council for Internal Organizations of Medical Sciences, 1956) (Box 27)
  - Retinal detachment (Box 27)
  - Retrolental Fibroplasia (Box 27)
  - Scholarships (Box 27)
  - Science and Government (Box 27)
  - Surgery (Box 27)
  - Trachoma (Box 27)
  - Ultrasonics data (Box 27)
- International Papers and correspondence
  - Africa (Box 27)
  - Bangkok, Thailand (Box 27)
  - Brazil - Koch-Weser, d. (Box 27)
  - Denmark, 1950, n.d.
    - Miscellaneous health data (Box 27)
    - National Morbidity Study, 1950 (Box 27)
    - Ronne, G. (Box 27)
  - Egypt (Box 27)
  - England - Researchers in Ophthalmology (Box 27)
  - Greece (Box 27)
  - Holland
    - General correspondence (Box 27)
    - Flieringa, H.J. (Box 27)
  - Hong Kong
    - Blindness survey (Box 28)
    - Correspondence re: Ulmer's trip (Box 28)
    - Ophthalmology research (Box 28)
  - 28, India
    - Basu, P.K. (Box 28)
    - Bombay, Lion; Indian Lion (Box 28)
    - Clippings and articles (Box 28)
    - Clippings and notes (Box 28)
    - Commission on International Economic Growth - Conference on India and the U.S., 1959 (Box 28)
    - Cooper, S.N., 1957-1964 (Box 28)
    - Galbraith, J.K. (Box 28)
    - Gerstein, A. (Box 28)
    - Krishna, N., 1958-1962 (Box 28)
    - Lazarus, A.S. (Box 28)
    - Mohatta, B.S. (Box 28)
    - Monnier, D.C. (Box 28)
    - Nain, J.L., 1957-1961 (Box 28)
    - Nehru, J. (Box 28)
    - Pandit, Y.K.C. (Box 28)
    - Rambo, V.C. (Box 28)
    - Schroff, M.S. (Box 28)
    - West, K.M. (Box 28)
    - Wood, C.T. (Box 28)
    - General Correspondence - A-D (Box 28)
    - General Correspondence - G-Y (Box 29)
  - International - France, Italy, Switzerland (Box 29)
  - International Cooperation Administration (Box 29)
  - International health - Miscellaneous data (Box 29)
  - Israel, 1959-1964
    - Feigenbaum, A. (Box 29)
    - Kornbleuth, W., 1959-1964 (Box 29)
    - Reprints and clippings re: eye research (Box 29)
  - Japan, 1956-1960
    - Correspondence and miscellaneous (Box 29)
    - Inouye, M. (Box 29)
    - Nakajima, A. (Box 29)
    - Nakaizumi, Y. (Box 29)
    - Sato, T., 1956-1960 (Box 29)
  - Lebanon (Box 29)
  - Mexico - Instituto Nacional de Oftalmologia (Box 29)
  - Norway (Box 29)
  - Researchers in foreign countries (Box 29)
  - Russia - Articles, clippings (Box 29)
  - Spain - Mier, L. (Box 30)
  - Sweden (Box 30)
- Congressional Papers, 1949-1969
  - Data re: establishment of Eye Institute (Box 30)
  - House Correspondence
    - General (Box 30)
    - Bolton, F.T. (Box 30)
    - Celler, E. (Box 30)
    - Elliott, C. (Box 30)
    - Fogarty, J.E. (Box 30)
    - Priest, P. (Box 30)
    - Young, S.M., 1949-1960 (Box 30)
  - Senate Correspondence, 1957-1968
    - General (Box 30)
    - Cooper, J.S. (Box 30)
    - Hill, L., 1958-1968 (Box 30)
    - Kefauver, E. (Box 30)
    - Neuberger, R.L., 1957-1960 (Box 30)
  - Related Correspondence - Quinn, L.C., Jr., 1957-1966 (Box 30)
  - Related correspondence - Quinn, L.C., Jr. - and miscellaneous, 1967 (Box 31)
  - House Committee on Interstate and Foreign Commerce, 1949-1960
    - Correspodence, 1949-1960 (Box 31)
    - Statements re: Eye Institute (Box 31)
    - Hearings, 1949-1955
      - Mental Health Study Act of 1955, 1955 (Box 31)
      - Construction of Medical Schools (Box 31)
      - Health Inquiry, 1953 (Box 31)
      - Health Plan, 1949 (Box 31)
      - Research Facilities (Box 31)
  - House Committee on Appropriations, Statements and Reports, 1952-1967 (Box 32)
  - House Committee on Education and Labor. Hearings on Scholarship and Loan Program, 1958 (Box 33)
  - Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare. Health Hearings and Reports (Box 33)
  - Public Laws re: health and research, 1950-1965 (Box 33)
  - Senate Bills, acts, amendments, 1949, 1957-1967 (Box 34)
  - House bills, acts, amendments, 1949-1965 (Box 34)
  - Resolutions (Box 34)
  - Congressional Record - Miscellaneous excerpts (Box 34)
- Bound Volumes, 1948-1970
  - Howe Laboratory of Ophthamology, Annual Reports, 1948-1970 (Box Volumes)
  - Senate Committee on the Judiciary. Subcommittee on Anti-trust and Monopoly. Hearings, Parts 18-24, 26 on Administered Prices in the Drug Industry, 1960 (Box v.1-8)
  - Senate Committee on Apropriations. Subcommittee Hearings on Labor-Health, Education, and Welfare Appropriations, 1954, 1958-1967 (Box v.9-25)